Ren d'Harnoncourt Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series III: General Correspondence, 1940s-1967
  - General Correspondence V, 1954-61 (Folder III.68)
  - General Correspondence Wa-We, 1954-61 (Folder III.69)
  - General Correspondence WA-We, 1954-61 (Folder III.70)
  - General Correspondence Wh-Wy, 1954-61 (Folder III.71)
  - General Correspondence Wh-Wy, 1954-61 (Folder III.72)
  - General Correspondence X Y Z, 1954-61 (Folder III.73)
  - General Correspondence X Y Z, 1954-61 (Folder III.74)
  - General Correspondence A-L, 1962 (Folder III.75)
  - General Correspondence A-L, 1962 (Folder III.76)
  - General Correspondence L-Z, 1962 (Folder III.77)
  - General Correspondence L-Z, 1962 (Folder III.78)
  - General Correspondence A-L, 1963 (Folder III.79)
  - General Correspondence A-L, 1963 (Folder III.80)
  - General Correspondence L-Z, 1963 (Folder III.81)
  - General Correspondence L-Z, 1963 (Folder III.82)
  - General Correspondence A-L, 1964 (Folder III.83)
  - General Correspondence A-L, 1964 (Folder III.84)
  - General Correspondence L-Z, 1964 (Folder III.85)
  - General Correspondence L-Z, 1964 (Folder III.86)
  - General Correspondence A-L, 1965 (Folder III.87)
  - General Correspondence A-L, 1965 (Folder III.88)
  - General Correspondence L-Z, 1965 (Folder III.89)
  - General Correspondence L-Z, 1965 (Folder III.90)
  - General Correspondence A-L, 1966 (Folder III.91)
  - General Correspondence A-L, 1966 (Folder III.92)
  - General Correspondence L-Z, 1966 (Folder III.93)
  - General Correspondence L-Z, 1966 (Folder III.94)
  - General Correspondence A-F, 1967 (Folder III.95)
  - General Correspondence A-F, 1967 (Folder III.96)
  - General Correspondence G-L, 1967 (Folder III.97)
  - General Correspondence G-L, 1967 (Folder III.98)
  - General Correspondence M-R, 1967 (Folder III.99)
  - General Correspondence M-R, 1967 (Folder III.100)
  - General Correspondence S-Z, 1967 (Folder III.101)
  - General Correspondence S-Z, 1967; 1 memo Waldo Rasmussen - RDH (2/15/67) re: request from International Art Program, National Collection of Fine Arts, about participation in Paris Biennale. (Folder III.102)
- Series IV: Directors Correspondence, 1949-1968
  This series documents Ren d'Harnoncourt's years as Director of The Museum of Modern Art. While Director, d'Harnoncourt worked with the Museum trustees and with the various departments of the Museum, dealing with both major policy issues and with the sometimes minute details which are part of the administration of any organization. There is correspondence with the departments of: Architecture and Design, Exhibitions and Publications, Painting and Sculpture, and with Education and the Institute of Modern Art - particularly with Victor DAmico, for many years director of the Institute. There is also correspondence with: the Museum Library and Film Library, the Photography Department and Edward Steichen Photography Center, and the Print Room. Minutes of Program Committee meetings are included, as is correspondence about proposed exhibitions, and material on the Ad Hoc Committee to study future policies of MoMA, the Building Committee, MoMA 25th and 30th Anniversaries, and the 30th Anniversary Campaign. Important, also, in this series is correspondence with the Registrars Office, and the Personnel and Production Departments.
  - Art Frauds Legislation, 1967-69; Correspondence, memos, and legal documents relating to New York State Attorney Generals Offices proposed legislation on art frauds. (Folder IV.1)
  - Art Frauds Legislation, 1965-67; Correspondence, memos, legal documents, and clippings relating to New York State Attorney Generals Office proposed legislation on art frauds. 1 TLS John Rewald-RDH (2/27/66) re: Roundtable Discussion on the French Law of Art, 2/25/66, at which three French experts spoke. 1 TLS Louis J. Lefkowitz-RDH (6/16/67). (Folder IV.2)
  - Museum of Modern Art By-Laws, 1960; 1967; Copies of MoMA by-laws adopted 5/12/60; amended 11/9/67. (Folder IV.3)
  - Barr, Alfred H. Jr., Lectureship, 1954-55; (1956-67); Correspondence relating to establishment of AHB Lectureship. (Folder IV.4)
  - Barr, Alfred H. Jr., 1953-67; Correspondence, memos on various museum topics. Some material on party given in honor of Mr. and Mrs. Barr by Mr. and Mrs. David Rockefeller in Tarrytown, 5/26/67. (Folder IV.5)
  - Barr, Alfred H. Jr., 1953-67; Correspondence, memos on various museum topics. (Folder IV.6)
  - Barr, Alfred H. Jr., 60th Birthday, 1/28/62, 1962; Correspondence and memos about the celebration of AHBs 60th birthday, and letters of congratulation from people not present at the party. (Folder IV.7)
  - Burden, William A.M., 1965-66; Correspondence. (Folder IV.8)
  - Burden, William A.M., 1960-61; Correspondence. (Folder IV.9)
  - Burden, William A.M., 1958-59; Correspondence. (Folder IV.10)
  - Burden, William A.M., 1956-57; Correspondence. (Folder IV.11)
  - Burden, William A.M., 1955; Correspondence. (Folder IV.12)
  - Burden, William A.M., 1953-54; Correspondence. (Folder IV.13)
  - Burden, Gardner, 1965-68; Correspondence. (Folder IV.14)
  - Franc, Helen, Senior Editor, Directors Office, 1959-68; Correspondence. (Folder IV.15)
  - Garson, Inez, Research Associate, Directors Office, 1967; Correspondence. (Folder IV.16)
  - Goodwin, Philip, 1958; Correspondence concerning dinner in Philip Goodwins honor, 1/6/58, and his death 2/12/58. (Folder IV.17)
  - Green, Wilder, 1967; Correspondence. (Folder IV.18)
  - Guest House, 1955; 1962; Correspondence regarding gift of Guest House to MoMA by Mrs. John D. Rockefeller III, and later sale of house by MoMA. (Folder IV.19)
  - Guest House, 1955-59; Correspondence regarding loan of Guest House to outside organizations for special events. (Folder IV.20)
  - Guest House, 1955-59; Interoffice memoranda and reports on Guest House management and finances. (Folder IV.21)
  - International Council Bulletin and Brochure, 1961; Correspondence, memos, and drafts relating to the production of a MoMA International Council bulletin and brochure to be written by Helen Franc. (Folder IV.22)
  - Iron Mountain Proposal, 1961-69; Correspondence, memos, agenda and minutes of meeting, 9/22/61, relating to storage of the Museums collections in the event of an international crisis. Minutes of the meeting are labeled Secret. Lists of the collections are in the folder. (Folder IV.23)
  - Johnson, Daniel LaRue, 1962-68; Correspondence between RDH and Mr. Johnson, a young artist who was helped by RDH to obtain grants, and to sell his paintings. Photograph of Mr. Johnson shaking hands with NAR. (Folder IV.24)
  - Kieslerm, Frederick, 1964-66; Correspondence, articles, clippings on Frederick Kiesler, architect and sculptor, who died in December, 1965. Flyer on exhibition of his sculpture, May-June, 1966. (Folder IV.25)
  - Koch, Richard, Director of Administration and Counsel, 1965-66 [1967-68]; Correspondence and internal memos about general Museum administration; also some legal and financial material. (Folder IV.26)
  - Koch, Richard, Director of Administration and Counsel, 1955-64; Correspondence and internal memos about general Museum administration; also some legal and financial material. (Folder IV.27)
  - Levy, Adele R. (Mrs. David M.), 1960-62; Correspondence and memos following the death on March 12, 1960, of Adele Levy, for many years a MoMA trustee. New York Times obituary. Photographs of the memorial display placed in the MoMA lobby after the Memorial Service for her. (Folder IV.28)
  - Rockefeller, Blanchette, (Mrs. John D. 3rd), 1959-61; Correspondence. (Folder IV.29)
  - Lybrand, Ross Bros. & Montgomery, 1964-66; Reports by Lybrand, Ross on their survey of the Museums organization and administration. Correspondence and memoranda relating to this survey. (Folder IV.30)
  - Candidates for the Board of Trustees, 1966-68; Letters and memos about the possibility of Dr. Edwin Land becoming a MoMA Trustee. (Folder IV.31)
  - Candidates for the Board of Trustees, 1965-66; Biographies of prospective Trustees. (Folder IV.32)
  - Candidates for the Board of Trustees, 1965-66; Correspondence, memos, and notes about prospective Trustees. (Folder IV.33)
  - Trustee Program Committee, 1967; Copies of outlines of proposed exhibitions and publications for 1968-1970 to be discussed at a meeting of the Committee on December 11, 1967. (Folder IV.34)
  - Trustee Matters, 1966-68; RDH and others correspondence with and about Trustees. Copies of letters from David Rockefeller and Mrs. Bliss Parkinson to Mrs. Simon Guggenheim thanking her for her gift to the Museum. Trustee Resolutions on the deaths of former Trustees, Duncan Phillips (6/7/66), and Henry R. Luce (3/21/67). Correspondence about a bill proposed by Congressman Jonathan Bingham of New York to provide for the establishment and operation of a national registry of art, March-May 1966. Photographs of sculpture by Robert Morris. (Folder IV.35)
  - Trustee Matters, 1964-65; RDH and others correspondence with and about Trustees. Copy of long letter (3/13/64) signed by RDH reporting on the Museums activities while its galleries were closed for renovation, sent to all Trustees. 1 TLS Edward M.M. Warburg-RDH (5/29/64) asking RDH to thank all members of the staff for their work in getting the Museum reopened after renovation. Trustee Resolution on death of A. Conger Goodyear (7/13/64). Press release announcing election of Walter Bareiss as a Trustee of MoMA (12/13/64). Copy of letter to William Burden from Clare Booth Luce (1/7/65) resigning as a director of MoMA. 1 TLS Adlai Stevenson-RDH (3/17/65) thanking RDH for accepting his invitation to take part in the Concert Artists Guild dinner for Bill Paley to be held at the Plaza Hotel on April 15. (Folder IV.36)
  - Trustee Matters, 1961-63; RDH and others correspondence with and about Trustees. Election of John de Menil to Board of Trustees (6/14/62). (Folder IV.37)
  - Trustee Matters, 1959-60; RDH and others correspondence with and about Trustees. (Folder IV.38)
  - Trustee Matters, 1957-58; RDH and others correspondence with and about Trustees. Report on the reconstruction and repair of the Museum following the fire in the spring of 1958. Reports on Museum activities by RDH to John (Jock) Hay Whitney when he was Ambassador to Great Britain (12/30/57; 7/11/58). (Folder IV.39)
  - Trustee Matters, 1955-56; RDH and others correspondence with and about Trustees. 1 ALS Blanchette Rockefeller-RDH (8/3/1956) re: meeting with William Fulbright and three Ford Foundation people planned for October 5, 1956. (Folder IV.40)
  - Trustee Matters, 1952-54; RDH and others correspondence with and about Trustees. 1 TLS Fleur Cowles- RDH (3/3/52). Correspondence RDH with Stanley Marcus of Neiman-Marcus, Dallas, re: a proposed Mexican exhibition. Brief correspondence between RDH and Andre Malraux 1 ALS Andre Malraux-RDH (n.d.) 1 TLS Andre Malraux-RDH (5/18/54). (Folder IV.41)
  - Trustee Matters, 1953-54; RDH and others correspondence with and about Trustees. Correspondence re: resignation of James Husted as Trustee, and election as Honorary Trustee, October 1953. Minutes of Trustees Meetings, 1953. (Folder IV.42)
  - Air Conditioning, 1956-62; Correspondence and reports on updating and installation of air conditioning in the Museum. (Folder IV.43)
  - Agreement between MoMA, Whitney and Metropolitan Museums, 1947-48; Drafts of proposed agreement between the three Museums. (Folder IV.44)
  - Museum of Modern Art and Whitney Museum, 1948-50; Correspondence, policy statements, and drafts of agreement between MoMA and the Whitney. 2 TLS NAR-RDH (2/11/49 and 2/15/49). Correspondence between NAR, John Hay Whitney, Mrs. G. Macculloch Miller, Lloyd Goodrich, Philip Goodwin, and RDH. (Folder IV.45)
  - Museum of Modern Art and Whitney Museum new buildings, 1949-50; Correspondence and financial statements concerning the MoMA and Whitney Museum buildings, and the MoMA garden - 53rd and 54th Streets. Correspondents include Philip Johnson, who was in charge of the project, NAR, Hermon More, Director, Whitney Museum of American Art, RDH, and AHB. (Folder IV.46)
  - Agreement between MoMA, the Whitney, and the Institute of Contemporary Art, Boston, 1949-50; A Statement on Modern Art issued in March 1950. Correspondence and news release about the statement of principles issued by the three institutions. Correspondents include AHB and JTS. (Folder IV.47)
  - Fundraising, 1950-51; Correspondence. (Folder IV.48)
  - Program Committee, 1966-68; Correspondence regarding proposed exhibitions; agendas and minutes of staff program committee meetings; chart and schedules of proposed exhibitions, lectures and symposia, publications, film program, proposed circulating exhibitions, national and international. (Folder IV.49)
  - Directory and Plan, 1966; Memos, draft and copy of the Directory and Plan of MoMA. (Folder IV.50)
  - Program Committee, 1965; Correspondence regarding proposed exhibitions; agendas and minutes of staff program committee meetings; chart and schedules of proposed exhibitions. (Folder IV.51)
  - Program Committee, 1964; Correspondence regarding proposed exhibitions; agendas and minutes of staff program committee meetings; chart and schedules of proposed exhibitions. (Folder IV.52)
  - Staff and Trustee Lists, 1964; 1967-68; Lists of staff and trustees. (Folder IV.53)
  - Program Committee, 1959; 1960; Correspondence regarding proposed exhibitions; agendas and minutes of staff program committee meetings; chart and schedules of proposed exhibitions. (Folder IV.54)
  - Directors Office, 1955-58; Inter-office memos. (Folder IV.55)
  - Directors Office, 1959-60; Inter-office memos. (Folder IV.56)
  - Directors Office, 1952-68; Letters and inter-office memos. Some correspondence RDH and Douglas MacAgy (1952-54). In 1954 Douglas MacAgy was Consultant to the Director. (Folder IV.57)
  - Directors Office; Natalie Hoyt, 1952-53; Letters and memos written when Natalie Hoyt was Administrative Assistant in the Directors Office. (Folder IV.58)
  - Committee on Art Education, 1952; Brief correspondence re: speech by George Dondero in House of Representatives, March 17, 1952, advocating censorship of the arts. Letter from Viktor Lowenfeld, Chairman, Division of Art Education at the Pennsylvania State College to Victor DAmico, Director of the MoMA Department of Education; memo from Victor DAmico to RDH. (Folder IV.59)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1966; Letters, memos, reports of the Ad Hoc Committee. Work of this Committee in 1966 was coordinated and organized by Nancy Hanks and Robert Armstrong of the Special Studies Project of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund. (Folder IV.60)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1966; Memos, bios of Trustees, lists of Department Heads. (Folder IV.61)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1966; Letters, memos, reports of the Ad Hoc Committee. (Folder IV.62)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Letters, memos, reports of the Ad Hoc Committee. (Folder IV.63)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Five Year Program, Department of Architecture and Design. (Folder IV.64)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Film Library Report. (Folder IV.65)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Five Year Publications Program. (Folder IV.66)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Coordination of MoMA Program. Report by Registrar, Dorothy Dudley. (Folder IV.67)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Exhibition Program from Painting and Sculpture Department. (Folder IV.68)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Library Report. (Folder IV.69)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1964; 1965; Report on Membership and Development by Emily Stone, Membership Director; Minutes of Meeting of the Development Committee (12/17/64). (Folder IV.70)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Photography Department Reports. (Folder IV.71)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Public Information Department Reports. (Folder IV.72)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Drawings and Prints Department draft Reports. (Folder IV.73)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Circulating Exhibition Department Reports. (Folder IV.74)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Future Policies of MoMA, 1965; Draft of letter of transmittal of the staff reports on the Museums future program to the Ad Hoc Committee of the Board of Trustees on the Museums functions and policies. Drafts of reports. (Folder IV.75)
  - Program Committee, 1959-65; Charts of Proposed Exhibitions; Schedules of Proposed Special events. (Folder IV.76)
  - Building Committee, 1967; Correspondence, particularly relating to alterations to the Whitney Museum building, 20-24 West 54 Street, which was taken over by MoMA in June 1966. Minutes of Building Committee Meeting, May 11, 1967. (Folder IV.77)
  - Building Committee, 1965-66; Correspondence, particularly relating to alterations to the Whitney Museum building, 20-24 West 54 Street, which was taken over by MoMA in June 1966. (Folder IV.78)
  - Building Committee, 1965-66; Correspondence, particularly relating to alterations to the Whitney Museum building, 20-24 West 54 Street, which was taken over by MoMA in June 1966. Minutes of Building Committee Meetings, Jan. 10, 1966, March 8, 1966, June 9, 1966. (Folder IV.79)
  - New Building Committee, 1959-64; Letters, inter-office memos, press releases about the new MoMA following expansion. 1 TLS Philip Johnson-RDH (9/10/62) re: Schedule for construction of the new building; plans of the new building. (Folder IV.80)
  - Building Committee, 1960-65; Letters, inter-office memos. Minutes of meetings. Minutes of meeting, 9/26/63, containing analysis of budget for the Building Program. Minutes of Joint meeting of the Building and Finance Committees, 11/28/61. (Folder IV.81)
  - New Building, 1964; Correspondence regarding the Grace Rainey Rogers inscription in the new building. Correspondence between William Burden, Harrison Tweed and Richard Koch about moving the Grace Rainey Rogers Memorial from 21 West 54 Street to the entrance to the new building at 4 West 54 Street. (Folder IV.82)
  - New Building, 1961-66; Correspondence relating to negotiations with the Whitney Museum and the Theatre Guild for the purchase of their buildings. (Folder IV.83)
  - Museum of Modern Art Reopening, May 25, 1964, 1963-64; Correspondence, printed invitations, guest lists, newspaper and magazine article. 1 TLS Abe Fortas-RDH (5/2/64) accepting invitation to attend reopening. 1 TLS Justice Arthur J. Goldberg-RDH (5/7/64) regretting that he will be unable to attend reopening. Notes on meeting of Ad Hoc Committee about reopening of Museum, Dec. 17, 1963. (Folder IV.84)
  - Mrs. Lyndon B. Johnson, 1964; Correspondence about Mrs. Lyndon B. Johnson officiating at the reopening of the Museum. (Folder IV .85)
  - Museum Reopening, 1964; Responses by newspaper editors to invitation to reopening ceremonies. (Folder IV.86)
  - Ground-breaking Ceremonies, 1962; Correspondence re: Ground-breaking Ceremonies, November 25, 1962. (Folder IV.87)
  - Prentice Houses, 1960-63; Correspondence, and press releases relating to the transfer of houses at 5 and 7 West 53 Street to MoMA by Mrs. E. Parmalee Prentice (Alta Rockefeller Prentice). 1 TLS Mrs. E. Parmalee Prentice - RDH (5/27/60) thanking him for his letter of sympathy on the death of her brother, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (Folder IV.88)
  - The Museum of Modern Art Builds, 1962-64; Correspondence about - and a copy of - the brochure, The Museum of Modern Art Builds. The brochure, which was published in 1962, gave detailed information on plans for the Museums rebuilding and renovation, begun in November 1962. Copy of article in Museum News, June 1963, by Emily Stone, Membership Director, on the Building-Endowment Fund Drive launched in 1959. (Folder IV.89)
  - Chermayeff & Geismar, 1963-64; Correspondence about the content and design of a new tourist flyer. (Folder IV.90)
  - 30th Anniversary Drive, 1963-64; Final report, March 14, 1963, on the 30th Anniversary Fundraising Drive. 1964 press releases on changes in the Museum following its renovation. (Folder IV.91)
  - Final Dinner of 30th Anniversary Campaign, Oct. 2, 1962, Correspondence about the dinner; lists of guests; opening speech given by RDH. (Folder IV.92)
  - Edward Steichen Photography Center, 1961-62; Correspondence about candidates for Director of the new Photography Center to be named after Edward Steichen. Appointment of John Szarkowski as Director of the Center. (Folder IV.93)
  - Photography Center, 1961-62; Correspondence about plans for the new Photography Center. Minutes of Planning Committee of the Photography Center meetings, 2/8/61, 2/28/61, 2/20/62. (Folder IV.94)
  - Fundraising, 1958; Draft reports re: fundraising and expansion plans. (Folder IV.95)
  - Fundraising Cocktail Parties, 1960; Correspondence. (Folder IV.96)
  - MoMA as an Educational Institution, 1960; Memo from Helen Franc - RDH with draft material for a brochure on the Museums educational activities. (Folder IV.97)
  - Fundraising Prospectus, 1960; Drafts of text for fundraising prospectus. (Folder IV.98)
  - Fundraising Prospectus, 1960; Copy of letter from Helen Franc - RDH (7/19/60) when he was on vacation in Austria, giving him details of work in progress at the Museum. (Folder IV.99)
  - Brochure: Today and Tomorrow, 1960-61; Copy of brochure, Today and Tomorrow, and memos about reprinting it. (Folder IV.100)
  - Honoring of Donors, 1959-67; Memos, meeting agendas and minutes about the honoring of donors to the 30th Anniversary Fund. (Folder IV.101)
  - International Council Fundraising, 1956-57; 1962; Memos, reports. (Folder IV.102)
  - Brochure: Toward the New Museum of Modern Art, 1959; Copy of printed brochure, and drafts of earlier versions. Memo from Alfred R. Crawford - RDH (10/19/59), with suggested amendments to brochure. (Folder IV.103)
  - Corporation Fundraising, 1959-60; Correspondence. Lists of potential corporate donors to the 30th Anniversary Drive. (Folder IV.104)
  - Grants for Study in the United States, 1955-60; Correspondence from and about students from other countries seeking financial aid. 1 TLS Lawrence Gowing-RDH (6/7/58) regarding possible financial help for promising young English artists wishing to study in the United States. 1 TLS Meyer Schapiro-RDH (5/21/58) about a French student at Columbia who is interested in museum work. (Folder IV.105)
  - Opening Dinner for 30th Anniversary Fundraising Drive, 1959; Copies of the speeches made at the dinner held at the Four Seasons Restaurant on November 16, 1959 formally opening the 30th Anniversary Campaign. List of guests invited to the dinner. Copy of a report on Gifts to the Museum and Greater Tax savings. (Folder IV.106)
  - MoMA Twenty-Fifth Anniversary, 1954; Copies of the 25th Anniversary Bulletin and Final Report. The Bulletin contains speeches made at the 25th Anniversary Ceremonies, October 19, 1954 by Dwight D. Eisenhower, August Heckscher, Dag Hammarskjold, William A.M. Burden, Paul J. Sachs, Robert F. Wagner, and RDH. Also included are photographs illustrating the Museums first 25 years. (Folder IV.107)
  - Expansion Plans, 1959; Preliminary renovation plans and cost estimate by RDH. (Folder IV.108)
  - MoMA Thirtieth Anniversary Committee, 1958-61; Printed reports on the Museums renovation and fundraising plans and progress. (Folder IV.109)
  - Photographs Used for Publicity, 1959-64; Photographs and negatives used for publicity about the new building and renovation plans, and for fundraising. (Folder IV.110)